This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine, online at
computer.org/software.
Developers, are you ready? It's time to
upgrade your data platform to
InterSystems IRIS.
Choose your language. Choose your tools.
Choose your environment. Collaborate,
build faster, and deploy more
efficiently.
When you can make faster decisions,
there's no telling what you'll create.
Ready, set, code.
Start coding for free. Visit
intersystems.com/try
to try IRIS.
Hello everyone. This is Kanchan Singh
for Software Engineering Radio. Today,
we welcome John Ellithorp to our show.
John's passion has been building
software systems to solve complex
problems, which he has done at many
companies. John co-founded Model N. He
was CTO there and helped grow it to a
global public company.
John is currently the EVP and Chief
Product Officer at DNA Nexus. I know
John through my network. John, it's so
great to have you here. Welcome to
Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you very much. I'm very happy to
be here.
Is there anything in your bio that I
left out that you would like our
listeners to know?
No, I think
you know, the interesting part of my
background is I started as an
astrophysicist
and then turned into software engineer.
So, I have a a strong appreciation of
both science and technology.
Our topic today is the role of a CTO.
You've been a CTO. There's a lot of
confusion in the industry about this
role. Many companies don't even have it.
Some companies call the VP of
engineering the CTO.
In your view, what is the core role of
the CTO and when is it needed?
The core role of a CTO is really to
understand deeply where technology can
be leveraged and to be able to
map that into the directions of the
business and to then use technology to
bring value to what that business is
trying to do.
What is the organizational hierarchy
though between the CTO, the CEO, and the
EVP or VP?
I think there are many different
versions of of this hierarchy. I think
if I look at the different fundamental
pieces that are needed in a company, you
need the technology direction to be set
by this
the CTO, the role of the CTO.
The engineering organization, typically
led by VP of engineering, but sometimes
somebody named the CTO, is used is
really the person that defines
the operational structure of bringing
the product to market. And then you have
the product organization that looks at
the market, tries to understand the
business needs, and then bring that to
market through the engineering
organization. So, all three of these
facets of the company need to be there
and I think that the structure of the
organization that has both the
product engineering as well as the
technology aspect,
um
these are parallel pillars in the
organization that need to be represented
in the executive team.
And the exact hierarchical structure
within a executive team is really more
dependent on the different skills of the
the individuals that are there because
what you find is that the heads of
engineering, the heads of product, and
the CTOs, while they have their defined
focus into their core areas, they
typically bleed over into the other
areas. And so, a CTO might actually be
well-suited to operationally manage
engineering. A product person may be
well-suited to
to understand more of the technology and
as well as understand more of the
engineering. And so, for example, my
role as chief product officer at
DNAnexus, I'm also overseeing the
engineering organization, and I have a
CTO reporting up to me. But, you may
have a an organization where the CTO can
take engineering based on their skills.
So, I think the exact organizational
hierarchy doesn't matter, as long as all
three pillars are strongly represented
in the executive team and drive the
direction of the company.
So, in companies that have the CEO and
VP of engineering positions, but no CTO
position, it would be the VP of
engineering that plays the role of the
CTO. Is that fair?
Uh for a larger organization, that's
true. I think that if you look at early
stages in a startup, so if you're just
starting a company, it's less clear that
you need a CTO.
You typically need somebody that heads
architecture and can rapidly build
something to get to the first generation
of a product.
It's not really until you get a larger
organization, you have more
mature products and potentially
diverging product lines, that you start
needing somebody to be able to really
understand where technology is going,
and also to to look through the product
set and define
how a roadmap of technology really
should look to be able to drive forward
in the what the company is trying to do.
So, so in that sense that Um, you can
operate a with just a C uh CEO and a VP
of engineering once it's smaller, but
once it gets larger, the
the
expansive technology
area, as well as the operational area,
gets too large for a single person.
So, I expect then that there's
differences between the CTO roles for
small companies, mid-size companies,
large companies, as you mentioned.
But, can you talk a little bit more into
what these differences would be? What
are the different skill sets?
When you're in a small company, and
let's say a small company is like sub 50
people, you're on your first version of
the product, maybe going out to the
second version of the product, the scope
is relatively small, and so what's
really important is to just have a
a quick first identification of what the
best way forward is, but then you spend
95% of your time building. And so, it's
more important that you have good tech
leads that have some architectural
experience to know where to go, but
they're head's down building, and you
don't tend to think long-term about
where your road map's getting you.
You're trying to get to the the first
release, second release.
As your company gets bigger, let's say
you're getting to the 100-person,
200-person company, your company's been
around for a few years,
uh you've gone through multiple revs of
the product, you might be introducing
new product lines,
that's when your technology decisions
start to become more and more important.
You uh
technology ages, so UI technology ages,
uh seems to age at the rate of about 5
years for every new technology, back end
technology goes a little bit slower,
but even with new SaaS companies, you
have lots of infrastructure technologies
popping up pretty quickly, and so you
get lots of desires by the engineering
organizations to leverage new
technologies pretty quickly, and so you
can easily have a case where you start
having more and more technology in your
organization and you really need
somebody to step back and think about
where it's going. Like what technologies
are really going to help the value of
the company and how you're going to
ensure maintainability, reliability,
performance, scalability in
not just now and not just in 3 months or
6 months, but in a year, 2 years, 3
years because technology changes and
take a long long time to implement and
you need somebody looking out pretty far
because the getting it wrong can cause
you significant challenges. So that's
what happens when you get into a
mid-size company. Once you get quite
large where you're you know more into a
thousand person company and more, then
the CTO I think turns more into somebody
that's looking at a very coarse level at
at technologies,
how they map the market to making sure
that you're moving forward but they tend
to move further away from being detailed
into the architecture.
So it sounds like there's a difference
between being a generalist which is for
larger companies versus a specialist for
smaller companies. Is that right?
I think that's true. I think that an
effective CTO at a smaller company not
just understands the technology but they
understand the domain that you're in. So
whether you're you're in health care or
a consumer based company versus an
enterprise based company, you tend to
specialize more into the that those
types of technologies. It's a little bit
harder to to move around. Whereas if
you're in a a large expansive company
with a big portfolio of products, it's a
little bit easier to move around because
you're dealing with very large scale
changes in technologies and directions
but you have less influence on the
specific architecture of those products.
Does the CTO have any management
responsibilities?
In my view, I
I don't believe that a CTO needs to have
direct management responsibilities. Um
in fact, it's somebody who grows up to
be um a CTO doesn't necessarily also
have the a track record of building up
their management skills. Direct
management skills, although they do
critically need to have soft skills to
be able to influence effectively across
the organization to be able to implement
the types of uh changes that they've
they'd like to uh see happen.
But I would say it's
in my mind, it's a little bit dangerous
to have a VP of engineering and is be
also the CTO in the same person
because the CTO needs a longer view and
a VP of engineering operationally has to
have a very
uh short-term view of getting uh
products out the door. And so, the it's
a rare person that can actually sit in
different meetings and uh and really put
on different hats um and have a a
long-term view versus a a short-term uh
a short-term view.
What does success look like for somebody
in a CTO role?
It's a little bit difficult to define
success. I think success usually for a
CTO is nothing goes wrong. So, you can
usually
you can usually identify when things are
going wrong more easily than when things
are going right. I think that when
things are going wrong, what you'll see
is that there's no clear path to the
architecture. There is typically less
rhyme or reason about different parts of
the product line and why they uh work or
don't work together, why they're certain
technologies are used or not used.
And
you'll also see that the technology part
of the organization does not interact
very closely with other parts, the
business parts or the sales parts of the
organization. And so,
what what that means is that you don't
get into the discussions about like how
technology can actually add value. And
so, I think that those once you see
organizations that look like that, you
understand that like there's there's
deficiencies in in bringing technology
to to the forefront.
If the technology is
a lot of times used as a enabling
feature of a company to be able to bring
value, but the true
like innovations, I would say, that
that happen typically in technology
companies are within the technology
side. And
in order to really explore where you can
actually use the technology to create
significant increases in value, I think
require somebody that can
both talk on the technology side, but
understand what the business is trying
to do. And so, if you see that
those discussions don't happen, then a
lot of times what will happen is that
you'll miss opportunities
that can come up where
you can make leaps and bounds and
potentially significant competitive
advantage because you understand how to
take technology and apply it in
different places. And so,
while
a lot of times you don't see these in
the short term, like you know, from
release to release, month to month, you
may see these things in the long term as
companies really try and lay down new
foundations in the future. These things
um
Good examples of major changes like
these are, for example, just moving from
moving into the cloud where it started
with a sort of ASP type models into
single tenant models into multi-tenant
models and such. All those are really
technology driven
changes. We're seeing another revolution
happening with containerization
and orchestration of containerization
and such. Those things can really drive
efficiencies and value to certain
customers and segments. And so, a lot of
those are technology driven and and are
led by companies that have strong
technology
people driving them.
So, if I could just summarize what we've
been talking about, what I understood
was you in the company you need a
long-term technical vision,
which is the CTO role. You also need
more of a short-term engineering focus,
which is typically the VP of engineering
role. And you need the product focus.
And the hierarchy between these is less
rigid. It could change at different
companies, but all these functions need
to be fulfilled. Is that a fair summary?
Yes, absolutely. That's a fair summary.
I view these different functions as
parallel peer functions, and they all
need to be strong
to have a successful company.
Let's drill into a little bit into the
hard skills. What are the hard tangible
skills the CTO should have? And I
realize based on your comments that
these could be different for somebody at
a small company versus at a larger
company, but maybe you could just draw
some broad strokes here.
I think as I mentioned before, the a CTO
has to be not just proficient and fluent
in the technologies that are applicable
in their area, but they also have to be
fluent at on the business side. And so,
that requires quite a bit of
really hard learning
both to maintain what's
your technical skills to a pretty deep
level as well as the business skills to
try and understand what the the company
is doing, how the company makes money,
how the company brings value to their
customers, and what success looks like
not just for the company, but what
success looks like for your customers.
Now, to be able to leverage that as a
CTO, another really important skill is
the ability to communicate to the
different parties in the language that
they understand. So, a CTO needs to go
back to the engineering organization and
describe what's important to very
technical engineers and architects in
that organization. They have to be able
to do that effectively. And
but then they could in, you know, a 5
minutes later walk into another meeting
and have to talk to business people,
whether they're product management
people, sales people, business
development people, or the customers.
And then describe how technology can
can be used to help them and what the
technology does, but in their language.
So, they can't get wrapped up in too
much technicalities. They really need to
fundamentally understand it and use
clear language
to be able to describe that. So, that
ability to change how you communicate,
but also really keep in mind what your
the value is to different parts of the
organization
is a critical skill. I think the
another important aspect is the
ability to keep up-to-date. I think that
this is
quite a difficult challenge,
especially as technology changes so
seemingly faster and faster as years go
by. So,
figuring out how to actually
maintain your not just a high-level
knowledge of what technologies are out
there, but really a tangible knowledge
of what is working and not working is
also critically important.
In your experience, what are some ways
of keeping abreast of these technology
changes?
There's the The easy answers of like go
to conferences and read blogs and stuff.
I think that gives you
a a pretty good lay of the land and some
high-level understanding about where
technologies are going, what's popular,
what's not popular, and such. But I
think that to get the part that I talked
about before, which is really a good
understanding of where technology is
going,
this is where you need to actually
leverage your organization. I think that
you have a an entire engineering
organization typically with lots of
engineers that are thirsty for playing
with new technologies. And so, having
people do little prototypes,
investigations of what technology is out
there, and really getting some hands-on
playing with technology, I think will
give you a better idea and having
discussions within your teams about what
would actually work and don't work and
why, I think it is a is very important.
I think that will give you more more of
a sense of what can actually be used and
why. And I would say that that also
applies across organizations. I think
that it's good to keep a network of
other senior technology leaders and have
discussions with them about what's
actually working in their organizations
and you know, did they try uh different
technologies and
and what was working out. When I was at
ModCloth and we were contemplating
moving to the cloud with a SaaS-based
product, we went out and you know,
talked to um at the time we were looking
at Node.js and
other technologies and we went out and
found people who actually did it. We
found somebody at LinkedIn and said and
they built their mobile product on
uh on Node.js and we had a long
conversation about what what was
working, how it was working, and the
technology was relatively immature at
that time. And but that was those were
very valuable conversations to
understand like really like you know,
practitioners in the world who have used
it can tell you what what's real and
what's not.
So, you started to talk about the soft
what I would call as the soft skills,
which is communicating to engineering
and product leadership and perhaps in
different languages.
So, can you tell me about some
activities one would do to practice or
acquire these skills?
I think
these are hard to learn. I think they
these are
I'm a fan of reading books about
psychology and typically management
management and organization.
And so, books by Daniel Pink like Drive
and Daniel Ariely Predictably
Irrationality and such really help to
understand like the motivations and
drives of people, and that really helps
a lot. I think the what you really need
to do is if I pull something from the
UX side, which is user-centered design,
my my view is that, you know, that
applies to almost every aspect of the of
your interactions with the world. You
really have to understand what the other
people that you interact with what they
really want, what they're trying to get
so that when you interact with them and
if you're trying to convince somebody to
that they should be using some sort of
new technology or change how they think
about what they're doing and and why.
You really want to have to have to
understand like what their challenges
are, why they've picked the certain
technologies that they picked, and
really be able to formulate your
arguments well so that you can influence
them in the way that you'd like. And I
think they those those are critically
important. I don't I personally don't
like organizations where the CTO has
their his own organization of architects
that that sit outside of engineering. My
my preferred model is that you more have
a single loan CTO, maybe like one or two
under. But that that CTO works with all
the lead architects in the engineering
organization. So the architects should
stay with the different products that
they're architecting to really so that
they have hands-on understanding of
what's actually going on with their
products. And then the CTO can bring
them all together and then talk about
what's actually working and not working.
And so that requires a CTO to have the
ability to influence people that they
don't directly manage. And so those are
that's a critically important skill. And
you talked before about ways to look
where a CTO is not working out well. If
you have a CTO that feels like an ivory
tower that, you know,
writes edicts and and, you know, the
engineering organization doesn't pay
attention to them,
that's somebody that doesn't have the
exact skill I talked about. And so
but I think if you if you have if you
can build that that working relationship
where the architects build not only
relationship with the CTO but the other
architects, that's where you can
actually have a very effective
organization. We have lots of
communication and real discussions about
where technology should go. But that
also affords you the ability to have
certain parts of your organization, like
the engineering organization, uh take
some risk, do some pilots, try out
things, and then inform the other
architects as well as CTOs like what's
working or not what's not working
because you need an organization that is
willing to have the courage to do some
tests, to do some trials, and see if
they work or don't work. Cuz it's it's
it's really only when you get hands-on
work, especially if you're dealing with
very large-scale or very large
complexity that you really need to try
things out before you understand if they
work.
So, you said that one of the way success
can be defined is the relationship with
the engineering organization and honest
bidirectional communication. What about
the importance of the executive team,
the relationship between the CTO, the VP
of engineering, the chief product
officer, and the CEO? How critical is
that?
I think the relationship between the CTO
and the
the head of product or CPO,
that's a very important relationship. I
think the just as the chief product
officer is trying to define
where the product should go to
to build value for the company, I think
that the CTO has a similar type of role
where they're defining requirements into
the engineering organization, but
instead of
solely to build value to the company,
although that's a a part, they're also
looking at building building in the
ability to scale well. I think what the
CTO looks for is that you don't ever hit
a wall in your future. Products are
usually built within a certain dynamic
range.
It says like, you know, it's a certain
range of scale or certain range of
customers or something.
And you can't build for everything cuz
you just don't have enough money. And
so, as you grow a company, you typically
will always hit those next limits, and
the CTO has to see those limits coming
and help the engineering organization
plan so that they can get through them
and and refactor to scale as the company
grows up and and increases the customer
base that they have, user base that they
have, and moves into potentially more
and more products that they might have.
And so, it's very important that the the
CTO work with the CPO to really
understand and lay out a future where
they jointly work at scaling up where
the products really need to go.
Now, um the CTO also has to work with
the sales part of the organization. The
typically, it depends how tech
technically advanced the products are.
In my organization, but the products are
quite technical, and so the CTO really
has a role to go and help the sales
organization describe
the value of the products, the value of
why they are architected in a certain
way, and how that will help the
customers directly achieve what they're
trying to achieve along their journeys.
And so, there's an
uh evangelistic part of the CTO role
that needs to be done, but it's also
very important for that relationship
because the CTO really also needs to see
how the technology is being adopted by
customers, and whether they it's working
or not working, and what the customers
actually see that the
what the tech technology trends are, and
if they're changing. And so, uh so then
that's a very important
input for the CTO as he goes and makes
his decisions about where road maps
should go. Through the road maps with
such interconnected
uh environments now, the CTO really
under has to understand where their
product is, and then how that's uh
interfacing with the larger environments
that are in the customers uh
on the customer side, especially for
enterprise organizations.
Do you have any examples about such
relationships that you would have
established either directly with
customers or through the sales team at
Model N.
Did you mean between within to the
internal people in Model N or did you
mean to the customers?
So, one of the things I got from your
answer was the fact that the CTO is
really a bridge between the sales team,
the product organization, and the
engineering organization.
And he communicates or has relationships
with the customers via the sales team.
Is that right? Or is there also cases in
your experience where you directly
communicated with customers?
I believe the the CTO usually goes
through the the sales team. The sales
team it's important the sales team
maintains all communications with
customers to really understand what the
customers are trying to do and develop
the long-term relationship with the
customers. But, once a CTO is engaged,
typically a CTO may
engage with either leaders in the IT
organization or sometimes the
research IT and other sort of different
facets of the organization that are
running technology.
Those are actually valuable
relationships and then you typically
find that within your customer base, you
may get a subset or a small subset of
those customers that have people that
are
at some level similar to the CTO in in a
customer where they're trying to chart
their own path forward
and really understand how they can take
the customers
technical environments forward and
really understand that. And so you might
find kindred spirits in other
organizations and I've found that in
different organizations and then those
are really valuable relationships cuz
not only can you find out what the
customers
are doing today and what's matching
today, but then you can really
understand what the customers are trying
to do and how they're trying to think
about technology in the future. And you
can use those relationships to really
bounce ideas off of, really understand
like, you know, is my road map really
like helping you do your road map? If
not, why? And
if it is, really how can we actually
make this work together?
So, what I really get from this is that
the network within the company and
outside the company is really critical.
Not just for
communication, but also to continue to
keep abreast of the technology, because
a lot of it is
a lot of this focus is obtained by
prototypes, which is done by the
engineering organization as well.
So, the network is absolutely critical.
Yes, so that network is definitely
critical. I think that
there's so much technology out there.
It's very difficult to keep up all
yourself. And there's so many people
experimenting that it's it's just a very
useful resource to to go out and find
out
things. And it could be as easy as a
half hour hour phone call. You can you
can find out way more information than
you did by reading a couple blogs or
or listening into
a talk at, you know,
uh service cloud or, you know,
Salesforce.
So, we've kind of talked about the role
and the skills needed for the role.
Let's talk now about becoming a CTO.
So, the big question is, how should the
CEOs and boards really think about
hiring? Is that typically from the
outside or grooming someone internally?
I have a bias because I grew from a
certain uh standpoint. I grew into a
CTO. So, I my bias is that I I my view
of a CTO they have to be quite technical
and have a pretty deep understanding of
the products that they are overseeing.
Um and so my sense is that it's better
to grow a CTO
than it is to uh bring one in from the
outside. I think that
that there's especially if you get to a
uh
a larger and larger company, there's so
many things that you learn by growing
along the way
um that are typically in the heads of
the engineers and you know the scars on
people's backs as they they built the
product,
um that that it's very hard to learn
that over time.
So, if you have people in your in the
engine- engineering organization
typically that seem like they could grow
that way, then it might make sense even
if it takes a few years, it might make
sense to cultivate somebody and mentor
them to to grow up that way. That might
be more effective than bring somebody in
externally. But, that's not to say that
you couldn't bring somebody in
externally. It's just the ramp up will
be slower, but you might need to
structure a little bit differently. I
think that if you grow somebody
internally, you may not need a chief
architect. I think the CTO can take the
role of a chief architect um if grown
internally. I think if you bring
somebody externally, then uh you might
have more need for the chief architect
or or maybe just lead architects within
engineering to really support that CTO
in terms of the understanding of what's
really happening uh with product.
Let's say though that one does have to
hire externally. How does that work?
Would you typically have had to have a
CTO title in the past to be hired as a
CTO? If not, what what other roles would
be considered by companies when they're
hiring for a CTO?
I don't think you need to
Well, if you needed to have a CTO title
to be a CTO, then
then there wouldn't be very many CTOs.
So, I I think that you don't need to
have one uh uh to be able to be a CTO,
but
just like uh any other executive role, I
think the obviously the place that CTOs
are generally going to come from are the
engineering organizations. Um they're
generally going to come from the the
technical sides, and so what you really
have to look for is, you know, it's
pretty easy to check the technical
aspects of their experience. It's really
the business side and those soft skills
that are the things that are going to
make them really effective.
If you bring somebody in from the
outside or recruiting, that's the part I
think that you have to stress and look
for. How effective um were they at um
influencing other parts of the
organization? How effective, you know,
you should have non-technical people in
the interview panel, and then have them
ask questions about like, "Okay, explain
this technology to me, but I'm not a
technical person." And do things like
that. Those are important aspects um
for the interview process for a CTO. Cuz
I think a lot of people make the mistake
that they assume that because of
technology in the title, that that
person is primarily technology,
therefore I'll just, you know, throw a
bunch of engineers at them and then, you
know, evaluate that. That's typically
the mistake. You really need a balance
of of people, all the people in the
organization that that person is going
to
work with, and and um really review
critically how that person can uh work
with um all types of people.
So, let's say you did end up hiring the
wrong person for this role.
What problems would occur? What are some
of the examples of deficiencies that
would crop up?
I think that
I as I mentioned before, the
the obvious things that will start
cropping up are that the influence of
the CTO will not be there. And so,
you'll see that the engineering
organization is really making decisions
outside the context of the CEO or CTO.
You'll also see that the CTO is not
being included in discussions about
where the product's going and such. And
I think that those are all the sort of
key indicators. Those are the ones that
will typically happen first. And then,
if you don't handle that situation,
don't identify that, then what you'll
see is the the
the more critical issues that come as
the uh the architecture of the product
starts to uh
become incoherent. Um and then you you
see that uh when uh customers start
asking questions about why like how am I
going to integrate with this technology?
How am I going to do uh like how did
your architecture help me here or there?
The CTO won't be able to answer because
they they just aren't involved enough.
And so, I think you know, there are lots
of things that you can do. But I think
the
uh it's really if you start seeing the
lack of communication, that's those
those are leading indicators. And
usually lack of communications
coming because of the uh an evolving
lack of trust and lack of respect
between uh from the organization to the
CTO because they the CTO is not giving
them what they what they want. Like, you
know.
Calling all developers.
There's no telling what you can create
when you upgrade your data platform to
InterSystems IRIS.
Are you ready to build the applications
you want, however you want them? Are you
ready to develop applications faster
than ever? Collaborate, build faster,
and deploy more efficiently. Tomorrow's
next breakthroughs are waiting for you
today. InterSystems IRIS data platform.
Ready, set, code. Start coding for free.
Visit intersystems.com/try
to try Iris.
Let's talk more about growing into that
role.
What is the role of mentors in this
process for someone that's growing into
the CTO role?
I think mentors are incredibly
important. I've been
very fortunate in my career to have
exceptionally good mentors.
And although I I I don't think they'd be
like they weren't explicit mentors,
uh but I
watching how other CTOs have worked to
really help me understand like what the
the real the real requirements of a CTO
are.
So,
um I think the you really need to
look at how
if somebody's growing into a wants to
grow into the CTO role, I think first
they should definitely try and find good
CTOs out there, whether they're in your
organization or not. Um it's always
better if they're in your organization
already, and then really see how they
work. And I think that will uh really
help. If you're somebody like me who's
already who I have a CTO now reporting
uh up to me, I think that highlighting
all those different aspects, cuz I think
that as I mentioned, most CTOs grow from
engineers.
And and they don't always see all the
things that need to be done. And so,
it's very useful to if you're going to
groom uh
um a CTO, to bring them into
conversations that they would typically
not think to be brought into because
they think of themselves as engineers,
they don't think of themselves as
business partners um in the company. And
so, it's really good to expose them to
conversations with sales, conversations
with product management at a strategic
level, uh even conversations with the
CEO about what the CEO wants. Those are
really good conversations to see like
what those people really talk about and
what they what they value and what
they're really interested in.
So, what experience would you want
someone to have before you started
mentoring them for this role? Let's say
they were interested in it. What would
you still look for
them in their experience?
When I look for somebody who
who wants to grow, I typically look for
somebody that has has a a strong sense
of curiosity and a growth mindset. And
also, somebody really not just values
technology for technology, but values
really
like how you can use technology. And so,
you can see that as people grow in
organizations, especially engineers,
where
people who are going to grow more out of
the um the core engineering role,
typically even early on their careers,
they're very uh, interested in things
like, "Well, what's the use case? Like,
what is the customer actually trying to
do?" Uh, they're very interested in
making sure their technology is actually
used. It's not just building it so they
get the enjoyment of building it, but
they get a lot of enjoyment by hearing
other people use their technology. You
you can start to see that people who
grow,
um
that's also true for architects, too.
They somebody's going to grow into a
CTO, uh, they start moving past just
those use cases and such and really
start asking questions about, "Well, why
is there value of this product? Like,
what are the customers actually trying
to do?"
And so, you'll see those type people
typically start having more
conversations with product management.
They get a little more interested in
talking about requirements and and less
about um
the technology.
And such and so, those those are sort of
the some of the indicators that you'll
say is like, "Oh, well, this person
may may be a good CTO." Course, that
person may also be a good product
manager, that person may be a good
architect. There There are lots of paths
that you can go
go for, but I think that they're willing
to to keep growing beyond where where
they were as an engineer is one key
aspect.
Okay, let's say I'm a VP of engineering
with an operational focus so far.
I really want to be a CTO to have this
long-term vision for the company and
contribute to the business.
What advice would you have for me?
I think that if
if a VP of engineering wants to wants to
grow into a CTO,
it's really starting to think
strategically about where the products
and company are going. And then
look at the portfolio
products and technology that they're
building and really understand how they
map together and
what
how they can be used uh in the future.
And really think about that. So, they
have
They really have to step back and think
about that and away from the weekly
grind of sprint sprint scrums, uh
project meetings, and and release time
frames. And so
So, I think that it's not easy. I think
that you can very easily fill up your,
you know, entire weeks just with all the
day-to-day grind. And so, they need to
be able to figure out how to to pull
themselves out of that and then spend
time really thinking about that. In
terms of being able to learn how to do
that,
that's probably where
a lot of conversations with product the
heads of product can really help. I
think they
uh to carve out time,
talk to the head of product, and then
say have the head of product really
explain to them
their view of where the value is of what
types of things cuz the head of the
product um even though they won't
understand technology at a deep level,
they will understand at a high level
what technology is giving them. And the
the value propositions and
differentiations of the product and
such. And so, I I would encourage the VP
of engineering to go talk to the head of
product, really understand that, and
then have have the time
to think about it and ask, you know,
probing questions to the head of product
about like, "Okay, what about like if we
did this and with this technology or we
did that, how would that benefit you?
How would you think about that?" And see
if you can get the heads of product to
to understand like, "Oh, yeah, if you
can
if you can do like if you can make this
happen or this happen, then that would
be very interesting." Start getting in
those discussions because that's where
that's where a lot of interesting things
can happen and the value can happen from
from the CTO role.
Let's talk about upskilling the entire
organization. We talked a lot about
one-on-one mentoring, but what are the
some strategies to upskill the whole
organization so they can participate
with the CTO in the prototyping and
evaluation of technologies?
Yeah, I think this is an interesting
question. I you know, I face that in
every organization I've built. We never
have enough architects and people in the
different areas.
So, I think that
you have to look through your
organization and then
really start identifying who you think
are going to be the people who are
going to help drive the technology and
the architecture of the product. And
then it's it's hard to do, but you have
to give them some level of time
to be able to
really have time to think about the
technologies. For example, my current
organization, we have we have budgets to
go to conferences for every single
person. We give people a little bit of
leeway to to go and do prototypes.
Um if they want to play with technology,
we let them do that for a little bit and
see if they can have small projects that
can help drive changes into the um
uh into the product.
And so, all those things are
important aspects to help
grow people in the organizations. I I
mentioned Daniel Pink before in in his
book Drive. He has a a framework where
he talks about um it's so-called AMP
framework where uh
uh A stands for autonomy, M stands for
mastery, and P stands for purpose. And
so, um for every person in the
organization, if you give them the
autonomy to be able to do their job
effectively, um if you give them the
time and um resources so that they can
master their job,
um but also importantly, if you give
them purpose so that they feel that the
job is important, then they will thrive
in their uh in their roles. And I think
that there are people in the engineering
organization, um every engineering
organization I've ever been in, that
align to wanting to be an architect. And
so, um I'm a I'm a big believer in
giving them enough autonomy,
um enough time to master, um but also
the purpose where the CTO can help
give them an understanding of like what
areas to look at and why it would be
important, not just for you know,
understanding what that technology would
do, but if you know, if they were able
to, you know, do XYZ with some product,
maybe a customer, you know, would be
very successful. In our world, a
customer being very successful
uh might create a new drug therapy and
save people's lives. So, I think that we
can tie very easily to to internal
motivation. And I think that those
things can be done to help bring out
people in the organization. Now, there
going to be people at all different
levels, and so you have to match people
at their level,
but in this world, it's really an an
apprenticeship type world. You have to
give people projects, you have to let
them do their work. Um well, the
projects can be side projects, but their
project can be mainline projects into
the product as well. Um but you have to
give them the opportunity to go and and
stretch a little bit and uh to be able
to make uh some level architectural
decisions uh under the guidance of the
CTO and other architects, and then give
them feedback about what's working and
not working. It's not only the ability
to make decisions and try things out,
but they they don't always know what it
means that something's actually working
or not. So, um so it's all it's also
good to um to to provide a strong
feedback to understand if
if something will work not just
immediately, but will it scale, is it
reliable, can other people maintain the
code, um things like that. There are a
lot of factors that have to come into
play.
We'll have a link to the book uh Drive
that you mentioned a couple of times in
the show notes.
So, let's talk about a typical work day
or work week now.
Was there a difference between what you
imagined and what the real day-to-day
life looked like for you as CTO?
It's probably different than I
think I had a a lot more meetings than I
thought I would as a CTO.
But I think the the CTO has There's a
lot of interactions you have to do as a
CTO. And so, both keeping tabs with the
engineering team and what's happening
and and such, you're you're constantly
being pulled into
the uh the front line of the sales uh
and such to be able to support uh,
sales, and talk to customers, and
and then working with the product team
to really understand what new projects
are coming in and what's important. And
then you have to find time to keep up
with technology and talk to your network
and things like that. And so all those
are very important, um, aspects. Um, and
so
uh, you typically have quite a few
meetings, but, um,
unlike engineers that typically tend to
hate meetings, this is, uh,
you know, these type meetings, uh, are
typically very empowering and very, uh,
insightful as you you're learning quite
a bit and and this is, uh,
uh, it's sort of a key part of your job
to really, um,
really like learn and take on, um,
uh, information. Uh,
sorry about my dog.
It's very important to, uh, to
learn all the,
the information that you get from, uh,
these different parties,
uh, and then have time to synthesize
them and then, uh, take action and
really understand where to go.
Um,
but there's also as CTO, CTOs typically
always have projects that are going on.
Uh, in Model N there was a major project
to to drive a SaaS architecture.
Um, their projects they're typically
customer facing projects that that may
be complex,
um, that require CTO. Um, and so there
are long-term activities that, uh, that
happen as well.
Can you comment a little bit about the
meetings? Who are these meetings
typically with?
I'll say that they're
uh, they're really a mix across the
entire organization. I think that an
effective CTO
constantly keeps tabs on all aspects of
the the company. So there's a very
internal aspect of working with
engineering and product to really
understand
what's actually being developed and uh
and then uh, uh released into uh
production. Those are very important
meetings cuz that's actually the
realization of the road maps that you're
trying to to put together. And then uh
but there are a lot of other um
stakeholder meetings that you have with
sales to really understand uh what's
yeah, as I mentioned before, what
customers are trying to do and where
they're going and how you how well your
product is actually uh being received uh
by the market.
There's interactions with business
development because typically
partnerships with other companies
um as well as channel partners. You
might have system integrators that you
work with and such.
Those are important aspects um and
typically very related very closely
related to the technology. Um you might
have system integrators build on your
product and such. Um that's an important
aspect to uh um to really think about as
well as as I've mentioned just
maintaining your uh network um and
trying to keep up to date of like what's
actually happening out there in the in
the technology market. So there and that
would include conferences and such.
What should keep a CTO up at night?
I think what should keep the CTO up at
night is really like what's going to
grind what's going to bring your company
to a halt. I think those are the things
that the CTO is the only one that will
that is really on the hook for making
sure that
the product keeps scaling and that they
that the decisions about architecture
are correct for where the
uh where the markets need them to be.
And so you don't want you know,
I'll take very obvious examples.
Nobody's building in COBOL anymore,
right? So uh things like that. So there
you know,
uh you have to really understand where
technology is going and and
it's not always the best technology wins
um unfortunately.
Uh there's a lot of mapping to
um the technology trends and what may be
working but also what's adopted because
technology um influences hiring and you
have to have people who can actually uh
build and use the technology and very
fluent in it. So, you need to be able to
understand if you can hire people in the
organization to do it. It's easier and
easier these days, but um uh but it's
also uh somewhat impactful for your
customers, too, if they need to
integrate with your technologies and it
has to map to what they want to do. It
has to map to overall architectural
trends. Um so, we had one trend from you
know, going from on-prem software to
single-tenant SaaS to now multi-tenant
SaaS. Uh and now there are more issues
related to uh privacy and who owns cloud
accounts and uh things like that. Those
are all things that really need to be
kept in mind because if you
if you miss a trend and then have your
engineering organization work for a year
or two down the wrong path, it's very
hard to
uh to turn that boat around. So, these
are all the things that, you know,
should keep the CTO up night uh just
making sure that you're going down the
wrong path and making sure that that
path doesn't have any cliffs that you're
going to fall off.
John, what did you like best about being
a CTO?
I love the fact that you have such
freedom of what you can think about.
It's being able to think about how
technology
can can be used in
extremely positive ways and
be
a key partner in the executive team to
really understand where the company's
going and
being the key enabler of of what a
company can do is uh
is fascinating and and one of the most
fun things I can imagine doing. So, I I
loved, you know,
you know, like being a CTO. Um I think
that it's one of the best jobs out
there. So.
Thank you so much, John.
Trying to wrap up now, how can people
contact you?
Uh sure, you can contact me on LinkedIn.
I also have a Twitter feed at JLohrke
uh on Twitter.
And we'll post those so that you can get
in contact with me.
Okay. Yeah, we'll definitely have those
links in our show notes.
It's great having you here today, John.
Thank you so much.
Great. Wonderful to be here.
Developers, take your marks. It's time
to upgrade your data platform to
InterSystems IRIS. It's time to deliver
complex mission-critical applications in
the fastest route possible. It's time to
use any data from any source. It's time
to embed analytics and create
interactive user interfaces. So, what
are you waiting for?
Choose your language. Choose your tools.
Choose your environment. Collaborate,
build faster, and deploy more
efficiently. Done and done.
Tomorrow's next breakthroughs are
waiting for you today. InterSystems IRIS
data platform, the fastest way to build
applications.
Ready,
set, code. Start coding for free.
Visit intersystems.com/try
to try IRIS.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SEradio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5.
Thanks for listening.